Thomas Terry Connally papers, Inclusive: 1896-1969, undated, Bulk 1934-1963
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Thomas Terry Connally papers
Inclusive: 1896-1969, undated, Bulk 1934-1963
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
123
Connally, Thomas Terry, 1877 - 1963
1 document box.
The Thomas Terry Connally papers include the Senator’s personal correspondence, Congressional speeches, newspaper clippings, and photographs. The collection focuses mainly on Connally’s political career.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Thomas Terry Connally, more commonly referred to as Tom Connally, was a powerful legislator who represented the state of Texas during the 1920s, the Great Depression, and the World War II eras. Connally was born in McLennan County near Eddy, Texas, on 1877 August 19. He was the son of Jones and Mary Ellen Terry Connally. Jones had fought for the Confederacy during the Civil War.
Even as a young adult, Connally was deeply involved in the public sphere. Connally received an A.B. degree from Baylor University in 1896 and a law degree from the University of Texas in 1898. Yet Connally set aside his legal ambitions to serve in the U.S. military during the conflict with Spain. In 1898, he joined the 2nd Texas Volunteer Infantry. Due to the short length of the war, Connally did not fight overseas.
Upon returning to civilian life, Connally was admitted to the Texas Bar and established a law firm in Marlin, Texas. He entered politics a few years later. From 1901 to 1904, Connally served in the Texas House of Representatives. As a progressive politician, Connally fought against powerful monopolies by co-authoring the Texas Anti-Trust Law in 1903.
After serving in the state legislature, Connally once again turned his focus to his legal career in Marlin. On 1904 November 16, he married Louise Clarkson of Marlin. They had one son, Benjamin C. Connelly, who would later serve as a Texas district judge (1949-1975). Tom’s wife Louise died in 1935. Seven years later, Tom married Louise Sanderson Sheppard, a widow of former Texas Senator Morris Sheppard. From 1906 to 1910, Tom Connally served as the prosecuting attorney for Falls County.
Connally returned to politics in 1916 when he won the House seat for the 11th Congressional District of Texas. After voting in favor of declaring war against Germany, Connally resigned his office and joined the 22nd Infantry Brigade. However, he did not serve overseas.
When the war was over, Connally returned to the U. S. House of Representatives. He was appointed to the Committee on Foreign Affairs where he encouraged his fellow legislators to abandon isolationism. He earnestly fought for American adoption of the League of Nations and served as the U.S. delegate to the Inter-parliamentary Union in Geneva, Switzerland.
After serving in the House for twelve years, Connally was elected to the Senate in 1928. His
reputation for oratory quickly grew. He served on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee for most of his tenure. He was active in creating the Charter of the United Nations in 1945 as well as garnering American support for the organization. As a Democrat, Connally supported the New Deal, but opposed President Roosevelt’s attempts to pack the Supreme Court. He is also known for proposing the Connally Act, a piece of legislation that prohibited the interstate sale of oil that had been refined in violation of state quotas. Overall, Connally served six terms as a U.S. Senator before retiring in 1953.
In 1954, with the help of Alfred Steinberg, Connally composed his memoir. This work was
entitled My Name is Tom Connally. Connally died of pneumonia in Washington, D.C. on 1963 October 29. He was subsequently buried in Marlin, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Thomas Terry Connally papers range from 1896 to 1969. This small collection focuses on Connally’s personal and political life. The photographic materials include pictures of Thomas Connally from adolescence to the end of his life. The correspondence series is comprised of letters that Connally wrote to his mother, his sister, and his niece. The literary productions focus more on Connally’s political life. The Congressional speeches written by Connally and other famous legislators (George Mahon, Lyndon B. Johnson, Tom Pickett) are included. The majority of the collection includes newspaper clippings that range from the 1930s to the 1960s and chronicle Connally’s political achievements.
Arrangement
This small collection has been organized into four series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, III. Photographic Materials, and IV. Artifacts. The correspondence is organized chronologically. The literary productions are divided according to the type of material.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 123. Acquired 1970-01-30
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Anthony Garland Adair papers, Inclusive: 1929-1966, undated; Bulk: undated
Leon Jaworski papers, Inclusive: 1905-1983, undated, Bulk: 1969-1982
William Markham Sleeper, 1913-1943
Related references
Connally, Tom. My Name is Tom Connally. New York: Thomas Y. Crowell Company, 1954.
Green, George N. “Tom Connally.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 March 8.
Kelley, Dayton, ed. The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County, Texas. Waco, TX: Texian Press, 1972.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.
Subjects (Organizations)
Connally, Tom, 1877-1963.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. Senate.
Subjects
New Deal, 1933-1939.; Nineteen thirties.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Speeches.
- Correspondence, 1917-1959, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains personal letters of correspondence exchanged between Thomas Connally and his mother, his sister Lila McKay, and his niece Frances Andrews.
  - Personal, 1917-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Literary Productions, 1896-1969, undated; 2
  This series contains newspaper clippings pertaining to Connally’s life in politics, Congressional speeches made by Connally and other legislators, and other literary productions. A yearbook picture and profile from Connally’s time at Baylor University is included in the folder marked “biographical materials.”
  - Clippings: General, 1934-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: General, 1940-1945 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings: General, 1945 November-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: General, circa 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: General, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: General, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: General, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: General (1 of 2), circa 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings: General (2 of 2), circa 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings: General, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings: General, circa 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clippings: General (1 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings: General (2 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: General (3 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings: General (4 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings: Obituaries (1 of 2), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clippings: Obituaries (2 of 2), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Art: Obituary, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Biographical Materials: Thomas Connally, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Programs and Invitations, 1950-1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Speeches: Congress: Thomas Connally, 1924-1928 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Speeches: Congress: Thomas Connally, 1928 February 9-1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Speeches: Congress: Thomas Connally, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Speeches: Congress: Thomas Connally, 1944-1952 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Speeches: Congress: Lindley Beckworth, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Speeches: Congress: Ed Gossett, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Speeches: Congress: Lyndon B. Johnson, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Speeches: Congress: George Mahon, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Speeches: Congress: Tom Pickett, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Speeches: Congress: Olin E. Teague, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Speeches: Congress: R.E. Thomason, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Speeches: Congress: General, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Speeches: E.B. Germany, 1941 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Photographic Materials, 1935-1960, undated; 3
  This series contains photographs of Tom Connally from his adolescence to his later years.
  - Photographs: Thomas Connally, 1935-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Artifacts, undated; 4
  This series contains three dimensional artifacts including Senator Tom Connally’s name plate for the Senate Finance Committee and a pin in support of Connally’s senatorial campaign.
  - Pin and Name Plate, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)